Miscellaneous Subjects Collection, 1856-2011
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Miscellaneous subjects collection
1856-2011
MS 392
15 boxes (6.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Includes small amounts of mostly printed material on subjects related to women, including aging and aged women, alcoholism, anarchism, costume, fascism, friendship, girls, Nazism, physically handicapped women, postage stamps, rural women, sex, sex education, female sexuality, single women, taxation, tobacco, and witchcraft. Material includes printed material, books, cassette tapes, correspondence, position papers, questionnaires, reports, memorabilia, and stamps.
The Miscellaneous Subjects Collection consists of material from several disparate topical areas that were viewed as too small or too esoteric to constitute their own subject collections. Subjects include aging and aged women, alcoholism, anarchism, costume, fascism, friendship, girls, Nazism, physically handicapped women, postage stamps, rural women, sex and sexuality, single women, taxation, and tobacco. The collection spans the period from 1856 to 2011. Types of material include articles, books, correspondence, leaflets, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, periodicals, position papers, questionnaires, reports, memorabilia, and stamps. The costume files include a collection of early twentieth century paper dolls and books on women's fashion. Other particularly interesting material includes documents relating to Mary Ware Dennett's approach to sex education for children and the obscenity charges she faced in 1929-30; the N.O.W. questionnaire on sexuality that Shere Hite used as the basis for her book on women's sexuality in the 1970s; and postage stamps featuring women.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected. Recent additions may not be reflected in the finding aid.
History of the Collection
Materials in this subject collection were either purchased or given to the Sophia Smith Collection by various donors.
Search Terms
Aged women--History--Sources; Fashion--History--19th century--Sources; Fashion--History--20th century--Sources; Female friendship--History; Girls--History--Sources; Handicapped women--History--Sources; Women--Comic books, strips, etc.; Postage stamps; Rural women--History--Sources; Sex instruction--History--Sources; Single women--History--Sources; Women anarchists--History--Sources; Women--Sexual behavior--History--Sources; Women--Taxation--United States--History--Sources; Dennett, Mary Ware, 1872-1947; Keller, Helen, 1880-1968
- Aged and aging (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Alcoholism (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Anarchism
  - General (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - French (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Cartoons and comics
  [See separate box.]
- Censorship: material from Arizona Schools and State Board of Education, 1967-68 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Charity organizations (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Citizenship
  - General (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Citizenship case: Rebecca Shelly, 1938 (Box 1)
- Cartoons and comics: feminist and lesbian comic books
  - Roberta Gregory's Artistic Licentiousness, 1989, 1994, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Come Out Comix by Mary Wings, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Dirty Plotte by Julie Doucet, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Dynamite Damsels by Roberta Gregory, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Hothead Paisan, Homicidal Lesbian Terrorist by Diane DiMassa, 1992-98 (Box 2, Folder 5-8)
  - The Little Prick by Zizi, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Roberta Gregory's Naughty Bits, 1-39, 1991-2004 (Box 2, Folder 10-15)
  - PePG!RLZ by Siobhan, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Scarlett Pilgrim by Trina Robbins, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Tits and Clits by Lyn Chevli and Joyce Sutton/Farmer, 1972, 1976, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Total Disaster by Fly, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Wimmen's Commix, various artists, 1976, 1983, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Twisted Sisters: A Collection of Bad Girl Art edited by Diane Noomin, Penguin Books, 1991 (Box 2a, Folder 1)
  - Twisted Sisters 2: Drawing the Line edited by Diane Noomin, Kitchen Sink Press, 1994 (Box 2a, Folder 2)
  - Women and the Comics by Trina Robbins and Catherine Yronwode, Eclipse Books, 1985 (Box 2a, Folder 3)
- Cookery
  [See also Oversize.]
  - General, 1926-69 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Mrs. A.L. Webster's Improved Housewife or Book of Receipts, 1850 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - The American Housewife and Kitchen Directory, 1869 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Mrs. Winslow's Domestic Receipt Book for 1874, 1873 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Mrs. Beeton's Every Day Cookery, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Choice Recipes compliments of Walter Baker & Co., Ltd., includes "Chocolate and Cocoa Recipes" by Miss Parloa and "Home Made Candy Recipes" by Mrs. Janet McKenzie Hill, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - A Thousand Ways to Please a Husband by Louise Bennett Weaver and Helen Cowles Lecron, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Frigidaire Recipes, Frigidaire Corporation, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - The Seducer's Cookbook by Mimi Sheraton, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Costume
  - General (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Bloomer costume (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Dress Reform (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Mini-Midi-Maxi skirts (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Paper doll family made by "Mommy and Aunt Sylvia," circa 1900 (Box 5, Folder 5-9)
  - Photographs
    [See also oversize.]
    - General, 19th Century (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - General, 20th Century (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Hats and Hair, 19th Century (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Hats and Hair, 20th Century (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Women's Work Clothes (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Children's Clothing (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Weddings (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Sports Clothing (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Bathing Costumes (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous images (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Books
    - Hansen, Henny Harald. Costumes and Styles, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Hunt, Mrs. Alfred W. Our Grandmother's Gowns, 1884 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Eleanor King's Guide to Glamour, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Rexford, Nancy. Women's Shoes in America: 1795-1930, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Ritcher, Mme Eva. ABC of Millinery, 1950 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Schmidt, Minna. 400 Outstanding Women of the World and Costumology of Their Lifetime, 1933 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Andrews, Ella Matson. A Century of Fashion, 1909 (Box 8)
- Fascism (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Friendship
  - General (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - The Friendships of Women by William Rounseville Alger, 1872 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Girls
  - General, 1940-53 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Historic Girls: Stories of Girls Who Have Influenced the History of Their Times by Elbridge Streeter Brooks; Leaders of Girls by Clara Ewing Espey 1890, 1915 (Box 5)
  - Girl Life in America by Henrietta R. Walter, 1927 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Start With a Girl: New Agenda for Global Health, Center for Global Development, 2009 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Jury duty (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Literature, women in (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Nazism
  - General (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Letter from William E. Dodd to U.S. Secretary of State (on the position of women under Hitler), 1934 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Materials related to Impairment, Disability, and Handicap
  - General (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Keller, Helen (Box 10)
    - General (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - "Commemorating the Harvard Final Exam for Admission to Radcliffe College": souvenir, 1899 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Postage stamps
  - General (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Commemorative stamps and envelopes (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Foreign (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Recovery (from abuse or addiction): Women's Recovery Network Newsletter, 1992 (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Rural women (Box 10, Folder 12)
- Sex and sexuality
  - General (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Clippings (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Conference packet, "Sex, Power and Speaking Truth: Anita Hill 20 Years Later," Hunter College, 2011 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Masters and Johnson (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - "The Myth of the Vaginal Orgasm" by Anne Koedt and responses (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - National Organization for Women (NOW), 1973, undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Sex Education (Box 11)
    - General (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Dennett, Mary Ware (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Sexual harassment (Box 11, Folder 9)
- Books
  - Davis, Katharine Bement, Factors in the Sex Life of Twenty-two Hundred Women, 1929 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Davis, Maxine. The Sexual Responsibility of Women, 1956 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Haire, Norman, editor. Sexual Reform Congress, 1930 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Stone, Hannah and Abraham, A Marriage Manual, 2 editions: 1935 and 1953 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Thompson, Clare M. On Women, 1964 (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Single women
  - General (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Hillis, Marjorie. Live Alone and Like It, 1930 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Rowland, Helen. Reflections of a Bachelor Girl, 1909 (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Taxation
  - Bowditch, William I., Taxation of Women in Massachusetts, 1875 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Smith, Julia E., Abby Smith and Her Cows, 1877 (Box 13, Folder 7)
- Tobacco: effects on women (Box 13, Folder 8)
- Oversize Materials
  - Cookery: The American Home Hostess Book circa 1935-40 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Costume
    - Oversize photographs (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Sheet music for "The Bloomer's Complaint: a very pathetic song for the piano forte," Philadelphia: A. Fiot, and New York: Hall & Son, 1851 (Map-case Flat file)